RG 033, Works Progress Administration for Connecticut
Connecticut State Library
Works Progress Administration for Connecticut records
1935-1944
Connecticut State Library
United States. Works Progress Administration for Connecticut
205 cubic feet
The Works Progress Administration (W.P.A.) was established in May 1935 as a central organ of control for the relief projects supported by the United States Government. In Connecticut, Offices were opened in New Haven, with later district offices in several other cities.
RG033
1942-011 (except where noted)
Historical Note
The Works Progress Administration (W.P.A.) was established in May 1935 as a central organ of control for the relief projects supported by the United States Government. Taking over responsibility for the work relief programs of the Federal Emergency Relief Administration (F.E.R.A.), which went out of existence at the end of 1935, it became the major agency in efforts to provide work assistance for the unemployed during the later depression years. An independent agency at first, on July 1, 1939, it became part of the new Federal Works Agency and its title was changed to Work Projects Administration. It was abolished on June 30, 1943, and finally liquidated a year later.
In Connecticut, Senator Matthew A. Daly was appointed State Administrator on June 8, 1935. Offices were opened in New Haven, with later district offices in several other cities. F.E.R.A. projects, workers and officials were quickly transferred to W.P.A. and additional new programs were developed rapidly; by November over 15,000 persons were on the rolls, and by the end of March 1936, 28,671 persons were at work on 963 different projects in Connecticut.
Scope and Content
Most of these records relate almost exclusively to the Writers’ Project. The Writers’ Project was initiated was initiated late in 1935 as a part of the Federal Project No. 1, which also embraced programs in art, music and the theater and was later to include the Historical Records Survey. Federal sponsorship ended in July 1939, but most of the projects were carried on with local sponsors (in many cases the State Library). The first undertaking of the Writers’ Project was the preparation of the Connecticut volume of the American Guide series, published in 1938. Subsequently many other manuscripts and reports were written1, most of them intended for publication by State or local government sponsors.
Also included are records of the Architectural Survey, Historic American Buildings Survey, Historical Records Survey, Church Records Survey, Manuscripts Inventory, Federal Art Project and American Imprints Inventory.2
The record of other W.P.A. programs in Connecticut must presumably be sought in the files now in the National Archives or among the archives of sponsor agencies in Connecticut.
Endnotes
1As early as January 15, 1936, a newsletter indicated that the editors had completed the copy on tours for the Guide, staff workers were studying ethnic group organizations for another major project, material was being collected for a guide to New Haven parks, people were conducting interviews for a folklore survey, the architectural survey group were getting out reports on 4,500 old houses and planning a booklet on Connecticut architecture and a series of town histories was projected.
2A good brief account of white collar projects in Connecticut, including a partial list of projects, is in
Professional and Service Division, Connecticut WPA (New Haven: Works Projects Administration, 1940?), mimeo, 31, XIV pp.
A copy is in Box 333.
Arrangement
Grouped by the following: Writers' Project, Guide, New England Guide, Coastal Guide, Pictorial Guide, Connecticut Fact Book, Connecticut Place Names, Ethnic Groups Survey, Town and City Histories, Histories of City Parks, Hartford Flood, Bridgeport Library System, History of Norwalk Schools, History of Hartford Public High School, History of Labor in Connecticut, "Patriotic Pamphlets", Studies of New England Life, Folklore and Folkways, New Haven Tercentenary, Survey of City Governments, W.P.A. Histories, Hurricane, United States Travel Atlas, Vacation Guide, New Haven Summer Recreation Guide, Coast Guard Academy History, Miscellaneous Writers' Project Material, Architectural Survey, Historic American Buildings Survey, Historical Records Survey, Church Records Survey, Manuscripts Inventory, Federal Art Project, American Imprints Inventory, Maps and Charts, Publications.
Related Material
Headquarter records of the W.P.A. are in the National Archives, Washington, D.C. Records of the Connecticut State W.P.A. other than those which came to the State Library have not been located; some of them may possibly be in the hands of project sponsors or State government agencies.
RG 012, Connecticut State Library. Contains correspondence and other materials pertaining to sponsorship projects by the State Library.
RG 032, Emergency Relief Commission, 1933-1937. Contains some materials on F.E.R.A. projects that were completed by W.P.A.
Copies of many W.P.A. publications as well as photostats of some unpublished manuscripts are in the book collection of the State Library; most of those produced by the Connecticut Writers' Project are also in this record group.
Separated Material
Papers originally a part of this record group pertaining to the "History of the New Haven Theatre" were withdrawn by the W.P.A. and deposited with the Yale University Drama School, May 4, 1942. Those pertaining to the "Guide to the United States Coast Guard Academy" were withdrawn by the W.P.A. on August 18, 1942 to be turned over to Devon-Adair, prospective publishers.
Index Terms
Organizations:
United States. Works Progress Administration for Connecticut; United States. Work Projects Administration for Connecticut
Persons:
Daly, Matthew H
Subjects:
American guide series; Architectural surveys -- Connecticut; Art, American -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Surveys; Ethnic groups -- Connecticut; Federal aid to the arts -- Connecticut; Federal Art Project -- Connecticut; Federal Writers' Project -- Connecticut; Floods -- Connecticut -- 20th century; Hartford Public High School (Hartford, Conn.) -- History; Historic American Buildings Survey -- Connecticut; Hurricanes -- Connecticut; Labor -- Connecticut -- History; Parks -- Connecticut -- History; Public libraries -- Connecticut -- Bridgeport -- History; Public schools -- Connecticut -- Norwalk -- History; United States. Works Progress Administration for Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; United States. Work Projects Administration for Connecticut -- Records and correspondence
Document Types:
Card indexes; Clippings; Correspondence; Drafts (documents); Drawings; Final drafts; Notes; Pamphlets; Photographs; Press releases; Project manuals; Questionnaires; Reports; Scrapbooks; Surveys (documents)
Restrictions on Access
All records except for the Ethnic Groups Survey are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
Most of the records in this record group were transferred to the State Library in May 1942, although some were stored in the Sterling Library of Yale University until 1950. The latter included the files of the Historical Records Survey (many of them later destroyed or lost) and the American Imprints Inventory.
Container List
- Series 1. Writers Project
  - 1. Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, mostly outgoing, with Washington Headquarters and others about progress and status of projects, with some editorial comments and criticisms. A general file of Washington correspondence includes material on the final disposition of project records.
    Arranged according to project and numbered A-1 to A-41.
  - 2. Contract file, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
    Signed copies of form "Request for Writers' Project Activity" describing the nature, scope, publication plans and estimated staff and other costs for each proposed project. Many bear the signatures of sponsor, co-sponsor and State and Washington W.P.A. officials. Followed by a similar group of copies of form "Application for Permission to Publish".
    Each group arranged by project number A-1 to A-39. Forms on the Guide, unnumbered, are on top.
  - 3. Instructions and manuals, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
    A small group of letters, memoranda and mimeographed items concerning techniques and procedures for work of the Guide projects, other Writers' Project manuscripts, newspaper indexing, library service and book mending.
  - 4. Publicity material, 1936-1941 (Box 2)
    Press releases and drafts of press releases and other information material, newspaper clippings, and correspondence pertaining to the work and the publications of the Writers' Project. Also texts of a series of eight radio talks by William B. Gardner, State Director of the National Archives Project (Survey of Federal Archives).
  - 5. Card summary of completed work, 1941, undated (Box 3)
    Index card record, by subject or title, containing information on source, number of words, date completed, file location or other information about finished copy.
- Series 2. Guide
  The American Guide series was one of the first, and in the event, one of the most successful of W.P.A.'s white-collar projects. For Connecticut the guide was published in 1938 by Houghton Mifflin under the title
  Connecticut: A Guide to its Roads, Lore and People.
  Work on it began in the latter months of 1935 with a staff controlled from the New Haven Office but working from several district offices as well. Project workers ("field writers") gathered factual material from various sources and reduced it to reports called "field continuity". This was then rewritten into "field edited copy" and later to "State edited copy" which was sent to Washington for clearance. Thus many files are marked "FC", "FEC", or "SEC". The later printer's copy and galley proofs have been discarded, along with many duplicates and slight variants of the edited copy. What remains, in items 9-14 below, itself contains a great deal of duplication.
  These files reflect the structure of the Guide, and other information materials about towns and their people, industries, buildings, parks and recreational facilities. There are also chapters on agriculture, art, education, Indian lore, music, architecture, etc.
  - 6. Instructions, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
    Mimeographed copy of a 13-page initial plan for the Guide, with an incomplete set of "Supplementary Instructions to the American Guide Manual".
  - 7. Administrative correspondence, 1935-1938 (Box 4-5)
    Correspondence with Washington office and others concerning editorial and publication details, with some correction and criticism notes.
    Arranged by subject.
  - 8. Consultant file, 1936 (Box 5)
    Lists, correspondence and memoranda concerning persons who assisted the Guide staff as expert, unpaid consultants.
  - 9. Field continuity, 1935-1937
    Field workers' drafts, based on their research work, together with related notes and memoranda. There are sometimes several versions of the same material, often with editorial changes marked. Principally concerned with the topography and history of individual towns.
    - Ansonia-Cheshire (Box 6)
    - Cheshire-Essex (Box 7)
    - Guilford-Madison (Box 8)
    - Middlebury-New Haven (Box 9)
    - New Haven (Box 10-12)
    - New London-Saybrook (Box 13)
    - Seymour-Waterbury (Box 14)
    - West Haven-Yalesville (Box 15)
  - 10. Field edited copy, 1935-1937
    Drafts of Guide material, as prepared by editors from field workers' continuity.
    - Subjects
      - Connecticut - Introductory essay (Box 16)
      - Agriculture (Box 16)
      - Chronology (Box 16)
      - Cultural Centers in Connecticut (Box 16)
      - Education in Connecticut (Box 16)
      - Education (Box 16)
      - Geology of Connecticut (Box 16)
      - Government of Connecticut (Box 16)
      - Health and Social Work (Box 16)
      - Connecticut's Historical Tours (Box 16)
      - Indian Lore (Box 16)
      - Industry and Commerce (Box 16)
      - Literature in Connecticut (Box 16)
      - Musicians in Connecticut (Box 16)
    - Towns (Box 16)
      - Andover-Bridgewater (Box 16)
      - Bristol-Essex (Box 17)
      - Fairfield-Hartford (Box 18)
      - Hartford-Ledyard (Box 19)
      - Lisbon-New Haven (Box 20)
      - New Haven-Scotland (Box 21)
      - Seymour-Wallingford (Box 22)
      - Warren-Woodstock (Box 23)
  - 11. State edited copy, 1935-1937
    Guide copy as submitted to Washington for approval, together with various preliminary drafts, related papers, Washington comments and corrections, etc.
    - Subjects
      - Agriculture (Box 24)
      - Chronology (Box 24)
      - Drama (Box 24)
      - Education (Box 24)
      - Ethnic Groups (Box 24)
      - Flora & Fauna (Box 24)
      - General Description (Box 24)
      - Geology (Box 24)
      - Government (Box 24)
      - Health and Social Work (Box 24)
      - History (Box 24)
      - Indians of Connecticut (Box 24)
      - Industry and Commerce (Box 24)
      - Introductory essay (Box 25)
      - Labor in Connecticut (Box 25)
      - Literature (Box 25)
      - Music, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Points of Interest, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Transportation (Box 25)
      - Tours (Box 25-26)
    - Towns
      - Andover-Milford (Box 27)
      - Naugatuck-Waterford (Box 28)
      - Watertown-Woodbridge (Box 29)
  - 12. Bridgeport Office file, 1935-1937
    Work materials and copy files for the Guide and other projects.
    - Field continuity files for the Guide (Box 30-31)
    - Work files for the Guide (Box 31-33)
    - Field edited copy for the Guide (Box 33-34)
    - Work files on other projects (Box 34)
    - Edited copy on other projects (Box 35)
    - Project reports on other W.P.A. projects (Box 35)
    - Administrative materials, contracts for publication, book lists, etc. (Box 36)
  - 13. Hartford Office file, 1935-1937
    - Tours (for the Guide) (Box 37)
    - Municipal government survey (Box 37)
    - W.P.A. reporting project (Box 38)
    - Towns (for the Guide)
      - Bethlehem-Canaan (Box 38)
      - Canton-Hartland (Box 39)
      - Harwinton-Salisbury (Box 40)
      - Sharon-Woodbury (Box 41)
  - 14. Tour drafts, 1935-1937 (Box 42)
    Drafts of tour descriptions, with weekly progress reports and lists of "points of interest" in individual towns.
  - 15. Map file, 1935-1938
    Maps of individual towns, with "points of interest" marked.
    Arranged alphabetically by town, each with a list of "points of interest." At the beginning are more general maps and some related administrative papers.
    - General (Box 43)
    - Avon-Bristol (Box 43)
    - Brooklyn-Granby (Box 44)
    - Greenwich-Monroe (Box 45)
    - Montville-Oxford (Box 46)
    - Plainfield-Tolland (Box 47)
    - Torrington-Woodstock (Box 48)
  - 16. Bibliography (Box Index cabinet, drawer 20)
    Card bibliography of Connecticut history and other sources. There are other are also smaller card lists on ""Hartford churches and sermons" and other subjects.
    Arranged in two groups: by subject according to the table of contents classification for the Guide; and alphabetically by town.
- Series 3. New England Guide
  This guide, apparently never published, was intended (like the state guides) to be made up of tour descriptions, chapters on history, cultural resources and activities, industry and commerce, labor, etc., and accounts of selected cities and scenic and recreation areas. Most of the Connecticut data had already been collected, of course, and needed only to be written to fit the regional plan.
  - 17. Drafts and copy, 1937-1938 (Box 49-50)
    Drafts, notes and copy for the guide, with some administrative instructions and correspondence.
- Series 4. Coastal Guide
  A guide to New England coastal waters was planned and begun in September 1937, sponsored by the New England Council. A substantial monograph history of "Maritime Connecticut", together with descriptions of Thames River and Connecticut River side trips, was completed and sent to Washington, but it was evidently not published.
  - 18. Drafts, copy and correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 51-56)
    A copy of the final drafts of the monograph history and the side trip descriptions, followed by voluminous but disarranged notes on many aspects of Connecticut marine and maritime life: commerce, shipbuilding, life at sea, early ships and voyages, yacht clubs, coastal geography, etc.
    Part of the material is alphabetical by town; some is arranged by subject.
- Series 5. Pictorial Guide
  A Connecticut volume in the American Pictorial Guide Series, to be entitled Connecticut: A Profile of the Constitution State, was prepared, 1940-1941, but never published.
  - 19. Drafts and working papers, 1940-1942
    - Photographs (Box 57)
    - Final manuscript, 2 folders (Box 57)
    - Working papers (Box 58)
- Series 6. Connecticut Fact Book
  In 1940, following publication of most of the State guides, W.P.A. decided to place "the major emphasis" of the Writers' Projects on the preparation of a series of uniform State fact books. In Connecticut, work began in June 140 and completed text (23 pages) was sent to Washington on April 7, 1941.
  - 20. Manuals, instructions and administrative correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 59)
    Unarranged.
  - 21. Final draft and working files, 1940-1941 (Box 59-61)
    Final draft, followed by working files
    Preliminary drafts and reference materials arranged by subject; some unarranged papers at the end.
- Series 7. Connecticut Place Names
  This project, sponsored by the State Library, was designed to determine the origin and meaning of place names in Connecticut and to collect brief historical sketches for each entry in a proposed published study. Begun in March 1941, the project apparently ceased by October of the same year without completing anything for production.
  - 22. Bibliographies and administrative files, 1941 (Box 62-64)
    Manual of procedure (March 1941), instructions, lists of cities and other political units by towns in which they are located, and bibliographies.
    Three main files, the first general, the second by town, the third by county and there under by town.
- Series 8. Ethnic Groups Survey, 1942-012
  A survey of the racial make-up of Connecticut formed one chapter of the Guide. This project, a much more extensive exploration of the same subject, was sponsored by the Yale University Department of Sociology. It resulted in the collection of a large amount of material on the various ethnic groups in the state and the preparation of a number of studies, not all of which were published.
  The project files were found in a state of extreme confusion; a few groups and series could be reconstructed, but the present arrangement is for the most part a rough grouping of similar materials under broad headings.
  The researcher is warned that folder titles are often inaccurate or incomplete. The following is a list (probably incomplete) of finished and edited studies:
  - 23. Administrative Materials, 1936-1941 (Box 65)
    Fragments of files including work assignment lists, progress reports, manuals and instructions, lists of files, plans and outlines of studies, bibliographies, etc.
    - Tentative Outline for History of Bridgeport (Box 65)
    - C.E. Triggs Director Community Service Projects (Box 65)
    - Writers’ Reports (Box 65)
    - Bibliography Dr. Koenig used in pamphlet on immigration, published November 1, 1938 (Box 65)
    - Ethnic Studies: Personnel (Box 65)
    - Ethnic Studies: Reports on Conferences (Box 65)
    - Index: Material on file (ethnic survey) (Box 65)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 65)
    - Index: Ethnic Copy on Shelves (Box 65)
    - A field workers’ manual of the study of life histories of 1st & 2nd generation immigrants, 1937 August (Box 65)
    - Instructions- (1937) Racial groups survey-reports, outlines (Box 65)
    - A field workers’ manual of the study of life histories of 1st & 2nd generation immigrants, 1938 November (Box 65)
    - Labor: labor organizations outline (Dr. Rodnick) (Box 65)
    - Connecticut Racial Groups & their characteristics: a guide for the collecting of data (Box 65)
    - Racial groups survey of Connecticut-its aims & objectives (Box 65)
    - Ethnic factors in Connecticut life-outline (Dr. Koenig) (Box 65)
    - Ethnic factors in Connecticut life-Joseph Youngs (Box 65)
    - Ethnic factors in Connecticut life- (a tentative outline) (Box 65)
    - Ethnic groups in Connecticut-a guide for field workers (Box 65)
    - Connecticut’s racial groups (a guide for the collecting of data) (Box 65)
    - Connecticut’s racial groups & their characteristics (a guide for the collecting of data) (Box 65)
    - Questionnaire for interviewing industrial workers (Box 65)
    - Questionnaire for the use of field workers investigation organizations (Box 65)
    - A social history of Stamford and New Britain- (tentative outline) (Box 65)
    - The Greeks in America – instructions for socio-ethnic field studies (Youngs) (Box 65)
    - Memorandum of growth of Worcester (Box 65)
    - Racial groups-bibliography (Box 65)
  - 24. "Ethnic factors in Connecticut life: a survey of social, economic, and cultural characteristics of the Connecticut population" (Box 66)
    Two copies of a typed manuscript, by Samuel Koenig and David Rodnick: with the assistance of the W.P.A. Connecticut Writers' staff, sponsored by the Department of Sociology, Yale University, Maurice R. Davie, Ph.D., Chairman. This is a major product of this project. Most of the materials in items 25-39 were collected or prepared as drafts or working materials for this study.
    - Part 1: carbon copy of "Ethnic factors in Connecticut life" by Koenig: Roderick (Box 66)
    - Part 2: carbon copy of "Ethnic factors in Connecticut life" by Koenig: Roderick (Box 66)
  - 25. Edited copy of papers on ethnic groups, 1936-1938 (Box 67)
    Short reports or monographs by field workers or editors on individual ethnic groups in different towns or on various aspects of the life and culture of ethnic groups.
    - Racial geography of Connecticut (mostly Hartford) Part 1 (Box 67)
    - Racial geography by town (mostly Hartford) Part 1 (Box 67)
    - Racial geography by town B-G (Box 67)
    - Racial geography by town M-T (Box 67)
    - Racial geography by town W (Box 67)
    - Racial elements survey by towns (1-43) (Box 68)
    - Racial elements survey by towns (44-90) (Box 68)
    - Racial elements survey by towns (91-151) (Box 68)
    - Racial elements survey by towns (1101-1159) (Box 69)
    - Racial elements survey by towns (1750-1802) (Box 69)
    - Armenians (Box 70)
    - Austrians (Box 70)
    - Czechoslovaks (Box 70)
    - Danes (Box 70)
    - English (Box 70)
    - Finns (Box 70)
    - French Canadians (Box 70)
    - Germans (Box 70)
    - Greeks (Box 70)
    - Hungarians all Norwalk (Box 70)
    - Irish (folder #1) (Box 71)
    - Irish (folder #2) (Box 71)
    - Italians – the companions (Box 71)
    - Italians (of New Haven) (Box 71)
    - Jews (folder #1) (Box 71)
    - Jews (folder #2) (Box 71)
    - Jews (folder #3) (Box 72)
    - Jews (folder #4) (Box 72)
    - Lithuanians (Box 72)
    - Negroes (folder #1) (Box 72)
    - Negroes in Connecticut (folder #2) (Box 72)
    - Norwegians (Box 72)
    - Poles (folder #1) (Box 72)
    - Poles (folder #2) (Box 72)
    - Russians (Box 73)
    - Scandinavians (Box 73)
    - Swedes (Box 73)
    - Swiss (Box 73)
  - 26. Occupational distribution materials, 1938 (Box 74)
    Working papers, analyses and tabulations of the occupational distribution of different ethnic groups, based on a name analysis of city directories. A statement on methodology is followed by analytical reports and tables and by work materials alphabetical by city.
    - Occupation distribution 3% sample study work sheets & notes (Box 74)